<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-02-19T00:16:28+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">etymology</title><subtitle>an open rehearsal space for unfinished thoughts</subtitle><author><name>ben</name><email>etymology@uchicago.edu</email><uri>/about/</uri></author><entry><title type="html">Every Man at Forty is a Fool or His Own Physician</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/fool-physician/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Every Man at Forty is a Fool or His Own Physician" /><published>2018-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/fool-physician</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/fool-physician/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It is proverbial that every man at forty is a fool or his own physician; yet we do not consider Ethics to include the art of medicine”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Henry Sidgwick,&lt;/em&gt; The Methods of Ethics &lt;em&gt;(1874)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;i.e. every sensible man should have learned to take care of himself by the age of forty. Perhaps this was more true in Sidgwick’s time; nowadays, even fools can live to forty and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;quotations&quot;&gt;Quotations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=6oaRAAAAIAAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA775&amp;amp;lpg=PA775&amp;amp;dq=every+man+at+forty+is+a+fool+or+his+own+physician&amp;amp;source=bl&amp;amp;ots=A0r-pKCY-L&amp;amp;sig=CD-EkglWEXWxwCUANThFrEsNd5k&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwiW5cuL0ajZAhWvVt8KHeo1An4Q6AEIPzAG#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=every%20man%20at%20forty%20is%20a%20fool%20or%20his%20own%20physician&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cassell’s Book of Quotations Proverbs and Household Words&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (1914) gives two citations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have heard that Tiberius used to say that that man was ridiculous who, after sixty years, appealed to a physician.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Plutarch&lt;/em&gt; De Sanitate Tuenda &lt;em&gt;Vol 2.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[Tiberius] was wont to mock at the arts of physicians, and at those who, after thirty years of age, needed counsel as to what was good or bad for their bodies.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tacitus&lt;/em&gt; Annals &lt;em&gt;Book 6, chap 46&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presented below in context:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have heard that Tiberius Caesar was wont to say, that he was a ridiculous man that held forth his hand to a physician after sixty. But it seems to me to be a little too severely said. But this is certain, that every man ought to have skill in his own pulse, for it is very different in every man; neither ought he to be ignorant of the temper of his own body, as to heat and cold, or what things do him good, and what hurt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Plutarch&lt;/em&gt; De Tuenda Sanitate Praecepta &lt;em&gt;W.W.Goodwin trans. (1873) sec. 26&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A2008.01.0178%3Asection%3D26&quot;&gt;Perseus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But even while his strength was fast failing he gave up none of his debaucheries. In his sufferings he would simulate health, and was wont to jest at the arts of the physician and at all who, after the age of thirty, require another man’s advice to distinguish between what is beneficial or hurtful to their constitutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tacitus&lt;/em&gt; Annals &lt;em&gt;Book 6, chap 46&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus:text:1999.02.0078:book=6:chapter=46&amp;amp;highlight=physician&quot;&gt;Perseus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cassell&lt;/em&gt; corroborates this account with a quotation of Suctonius (which I was unable to cross reference) that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;From the age of thirty, [Tiberius] ruled himself according to his own judgment wihtout the help or advice of the physicians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Suctonius&lt;/em&gt; Tiberius &lt;em&gt;chap. 68&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>ben</name><email>etymology@uchicago.edu</email><uri>/about/</uri></author><category term="idioms" /><category term="sidgwick" /><summary type="html">Sidgwick cites superannuated saying</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">‘Execution’ I: The Actual Death Penalty</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/dp1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="'Execution' I: The Actual Death Penalty" /><published>2018-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/dp1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/dp1/">&lt;p&gt;(This post is one of a series on the death penalty. You can find the others &lt;a href=&quot;/categories/#death-penalty&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently spoke in a public debate on the abolition of the death penalty, arguing against abolition. In researching my position (a position which I wouldn’t defend in private conversation) I realized that the debate over state executions has far broader consequences than I had anticipated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A brief survey of the literature turns up many texts on the history of the death penalty and on strategies for abolition, but very few “pro death penalty” texts. In general the “academic stance” is one of opposition, and the focus of most scholarship is not even &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; we ought to eliminate the death penalty so much as &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to effect that goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope to use this series to compile some of the thoughts I’ve had about the death penalty. Each post will discuss an aspect of the debate: an argument, a perspective, a historical trend. Though the stance I adopted for the sake of the debate was anti-abolitionist, I am not convinced of the position. Although I personally believe that the death penalty rarely, if ever, be applied, I find the literature on abolition insufficiently self-critical, a fault which I hope to emend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before turning to philosophical arguments in later posts, I will briefly discuss practical concerns about the actual application of the death penalty in the United States. I don’t think that this evidence is enough to necessitate the abolition of the death penalty, but it may suggest a moratorium on such punishment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;executions-here-and-abroad&quot;&gt;Executions, Here and Abroad&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State use of capital punishment has been in decline in the 20th and 21th centuries. After the World Wars, a European nations successively moved to ban the use of capital punishment (for war- and peacetime offenses), sometimes as a prerequisite for becoming a member of the EU. Since 2009, the only exception has been Belarus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All Latin American states, Canada, and 19 US states have banned the use of capital punishment in peacetime. Australia, New Zealand, and about half of the African nations have also banned it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United States, too, saw a nationwide hiatus in executions from 1967 to 1976 due to the 1976 ruling of Furman v. Georgia, which struck down capital punishment statutes and reduced all pending death sentences to life sentences, although it did not declare the death penalty to be unconstitutional per se. Executions resumed following the 1977 reinstatement of the constitutionality of the death sentence and increased in subsequent years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, in the “developed world,” the 31 US states and the federal government are unusual in their retention of the death penalty, which has been a topic of heated public debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the United States, approval for capital punishment hovers around 50-60%. The supreme court has continued to apply ever tighter restrictions on the application of the death penalty: it may not be mandatory, it may not be applied to those who offended as minors, and may not be applied to the insane, and generally may not be applied for non-capital crimes. These rulings are in keeping with the doctrine that the death penalty is not inherently cruel and unusual, although its application should be restricted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;concerns&quot;&gt;Concerns&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the practical concerns regarding the application of the death penalty, racial bias among the most concerning. The death penalty, pre-Furman, shows a strong bias towards executing Blacks, and some scholars have linked its application to the practice of racially based lynching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post-Furman, it is generally accepted that there is no significant racial bias on the &lt;em&gt;perpetrator’s&lt;/em&gt; race, but there is bias on the &lt;em&gt;victim’s&lt;/em&gt; race, in executions for capital crimes. The state, in general, is more likely to execute if the victim is white than if the victim is black. This is a troubling indication that perhaps, statistically “Black Lives (don’t) Matter” when it comes to the lives of murder victims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, the same study shows that the total rate of execution for whites is about twice that of the rate of execution for blacks (7.8% vs 3.8%).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the supreme court has ruled that while the presence of a racial bias should be rectified, it is not in itself cause to reason that the death penalty is unconstitutional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The death penalty is enormously expensive in the United States, primarily due to legal costs associated with the complex capital appeals process. Nonetheless, 11% of executees post-Furman were volunteers (i.e. they waived their right to present mitigating evidence at their sentencing trial). Their legal costs are undoubtedly less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While studies on the cost of housing an inmate for life (and most are not in fact housed for the remainder of their natural lives) vary in their estimates, most agree that, as implemented and for most kinds of criminals, the costs associated with execution are greater than those of life imprisonment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-burden-of-proof&quot;&gt;The Burden of Proof&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Practical concerns aside, who has the burden of proof? That is, should we presume capital punishment morally justified unless proven otherwise, or vice versa?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the one hand, basic principles of liberal democracies assert that the state may not invade upon the lives of its citizens unless doing so provably achieves some justly some aim which its constituents license it to seek. This manifests itself in the Principle of Minimal Invasion: the state must use the least invasive means possible to achieve its legitimate goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other, consider a Hobbesian sovereign which derives its power from its monopoly on lethal force, a monopoly which can hardly be effective without any actual killing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it is a fact that states kill, most now also use softer tools to control human life: welfare, regulation, indoctrination, in the manner of a Foucauldian “bio-power” which is now involved in “fostering/letting die” as well as “killing/clemency. One way to view this shift is as a move towards “lesser invasion” inasmuch as killing is the ultimate bodily invasion. In light of this, the burden of proof seems to be on advocates of the death penalty, to demonstrate why no less invasive measure serves the same public aim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already apparent is the relationship between the death penalty and the theory of sovereignty, which I will take up in the next post.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>ben</name><email>etymology@uchicago.edu</email><uri>/about/</uri></author><category term="death" /><category term="politics" /><summary type="html">A brief summary of the current application of the death penalty the burden of proof</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“My Neighbor Totoro” still moves me</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/totoro/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;My Neighbor Totoro&quot; still moves me" /><published>2018-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/totoro</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/totoro/">&lt;p&gt;On Saturday evening (1/27) I went to see “My Neighbor Totoro” at UChicago’s student-run film society, Doc Films, in a special 30th anniversary screening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Totoro was my introduction to Japanese animation and I have fond memories of watching it as a child. Like the protagonistic sisters Satsuki and Mei, I spent many summer days playing in my family’s garden or the forests on the margin of the playground, hoping to catch a glimpse of Totoro or at least a rabbit or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the familiar plot unfolded, I grew nostalgic yet confused. While I was holding back tears, first time viewers (or so I presume) were laughing around me. My sadness was momentary, but the incongruity confirmed to me that the film which I had loved a child was lost. More precisely, my eyes had changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(The following review contains spoilers)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;responsibilities&quot;&gt;Responsibilities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We meet the Kusakabe family (Satsuki, Mei, and father Tatsuo) aboard an improbably laden jalopy, rattling its way through the Japanese countryside. We later learn that they are relocating to the countryside, closer to the hospital where their mother is convalescing. The predominant affect is one of radiant joy. Tatsuo stands with his arms akimbo, wearing a pleased smile. Satsuki and Mei laugh as they cartwheel around the yard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Satsuki, not her father, seems to be in charge of the move. As will later learn, her father is well meaning but absent minded. While he’s never depicted as negligent, it is telling that he is absent both times Mei goes missing: the first time buried in papers, the second time  off at the university. On each occasion, it falls upon Satsuki to recover her sister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Satsuki’s acceptance of familial responsibility is heartfelt. She certainly never resents or questions duty, just as every character in Totoro (in a properly Japanese way) play their role in roral society. Though Satsuki is in late elementary school at the latest, for much of the film she acts &lt;em&gt;in loco parentis&lt;/em&gt;, most critically when Mei goes missing the second time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Satsuki runs for miles looking for Mei, following the same roads as the moving truck did some months before. This time, though, she is utterly alone. A farmer by the side of the road is of no help. Two passers-by on a motorcycle offer little more than surprise at the great distance which she has just run. Their dismissal pained me, but elicited laughs from the theater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her ordeal ends quickly, though. In a deus-ex-machina, Totoro and his companions find Mei, reunite the Kusakabe family, and tie up any loose ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the closing scene, the mother jokes that she wants to “spoil” the children for a while when she comes home. They all laugh, everything seems back to normal. But how could it be? Having so lately contemplated the death of her sister and mother, how could Satsuki just “go back to normal?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lets-laugh-to-keep-ghosts-away&quot;&gt;“Let’s laugh to keep ghosts away”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Near the beginning of the film, the girls and their father are taking a bath when a miraculously strong wind shakes the house. Their father puts on silly faces and encourages them to (as subtitled) “laugh to keep the bogeymen away.” Their forced laughs turn to real ones as they play in the bath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I watched this scene I felt uncomfortable. These antics are merely a distraction: the emotion is forced. On this logic, the fear that the house might fall down cannot be real if the laughter is real. But this cannot erase far greater fears of personal loss and change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laughter sublimates worry, but ultimately cannot resolve its root causes. Tatsuo cannot inhabit his daughters’ world: he can only view it from the outside. And inasmuch as he is not an imanent participant in their internal emotional lives, he cannot air their innermost feelings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;embodying-totoro&quot;&gt;Embodying Totoro&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Satsuki is the only ensemble member who meaningfully reflects on the possibility of loss. She is the only one to voice concern for her mother’s health. Perhaps this is why it is also she is also most able to interface with the magical world of “Totoro,” interacting with him when loss seems to be at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Satsuki first encounters Totoro in a moment of concern, after her father fails to return home on the bus. Totoro appears beside them, and amuses them. Before departing, he gives Satusuki a package of seeds, and when their father returns moments later their excitement at meeting Totoro has washed away their worry and fatigue. Later, Totoro and company help Satsuki and Mei sprout those seeds while they sleep, “setting down roots” in their new home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Totoro embodies the way that imaginative play helps children to resolve worries which are beyond their capacity to express. Satsuki and Mei turn challenging situations into adventures with Totoro, allowing them to work through difficult emotions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;teleology&quot;&gt;Teleology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this (admittedly bizarre) reading of Totoro as a sort of friendly bogeyman, an embodiment of childhood anxieties is self-indulgently autobiographical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as a more reasoned explanation, I’ll instead air some thoughts on the similarities between Totoro and Spirited Away, arguing that key themes introduced in the former are only fully explored in the latter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both feature a strong female protagonist (Satsuki/Chihiro) who, while moving, enters a mystical land where her feelings of alienation and dislocation become embodied in fantastic beings (Totoro/Spirits) which she must supplicate in order to overcoming her fears and set down roots in her new home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Viewed in this sense, Spirited Away is by far the more effective film. There, we feel a loneliness in Sen/Chihiro that we only glimpse in Satsuki, and the thematic material is much more evenly worked, the cast pruned to place the focus on the central drama of the heroine: the object of care, Mei replaced by Chihiro/Sen’s parents, turned into pigs (the time that they are pigs is akin ot the time that the father is at the university) and the token character of the ailing mother is cut altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To compare the films is to suggest a teleological concept of Ghibli’s filmography. This argument is indefensible, but maybe it’s an interesting supposition on this, the thirtieth anniversary of Ghibli’s most beloved film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-wrong-with-cute&quot;&gt;What’s wrong with cute?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Totoro remains popular with good reason. At least for me, the luminous settings and earnest characters remind me of the magical (if perhaps totally imaginary) summers of childhood. Yet others, like that of Mei sitting by solemn stone statues on a forlorn hillside in the setting sun, or of Satsuki frantically search for her sister, remain as well, unsettling me still.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had hoped that Totoro would revive those childhood joys. Still charming as ever, Totoro had a different tone for me. I hope that it will be as different the next time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>ben</name><email>etymology@uchicago.edu</email><uri>/about/</uri></author><category term="review" /><category term="Doc Films" /><category term="Studio Ghibli" /><summary type="html">A favorite childhood film now feels sad. What changed?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rehearsal (n.)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/rehearsal/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rehearsal (n.)" /><published>2018-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/rehearsal</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/rehearsal/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;(1570s) a practice or trial performance of a play or other work for later public performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The verb “to rehearse” (13c. “to repeat, give an account of”) comes from Old French “rehercier” (to go over again, repeat) which in turn derives from OFr. “herse” (harrow), a rake like implement which is dragged across a plowed field to break up clods, remove weeds, and cover seeds. The modern sense comes from the late 16th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compare also “hirsute” (hairy, spiny) and “hearse” (a funeral coach), originally a wood or metal framework which held the mortuary cloth over the bier or coffin, called a “herse” for its resemblance to farm tool. The term synecdochically came to refer to the coffin and the vehicle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etymonline.com/word/rehearse&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Think of the long trip home.
Should we have stayed at home and thought of here?
...
“Is it lack of imagination that makes us come
to imagined places, not just stay at home?
Or could Pascal have been not entirely right
about just sitting quietly in one’s room?

Continent, city, country, society:
the choice is never wide and never free.
And here, or there ... No. Should we have stayed at home,
wherever that may be?”
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;– from Elizabeth Bishop, “Questions of Travel”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To a fault, my mental activity is dictated by my environment. I require distinct spaces for sleep, socialization, reflection. I’m probably not alone in this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It recently occurred to me that the spaces most conducive to my creativity are liminal: spaces like the intimate recital hall, convivial dinner table, coffee shop, or reading room, which blend privacy and exposure, familiarity and novelty, in turn fostering a productive balance between contemplation and expression, reduction and synthesis. When these forces are properly balanced, my mind can spin taut conceptual webs. Too much tension and the mental filament tears. Too little and the web is formless, slack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this blog will be a virtual creative space for the elaboration of my thoughts: a place to try out ideas before a forgiving audience, for mental “re-hearsal,” its content somewhere between a transcript of my internal monologue and a polished work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thank my first and most forgiving audience – my friends – for their sound advice and for engaging me in helpful conversation, even when it was tedious. Although they are not to blame for this (mis)adventure, it would not have come to light without their encouragement. My particular thanks go to Emily for arguing that this blog could achieve something more than indecent academic exposure and to Ronen for inspiring me to start. I am motivated by the thought that you might be reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-ben&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>ben</name><email>etymology@uchicago.edu</email><uri>/about/</uri></author><category term="personal" /><category term="creativity" /><summary type="html">(1570s) a practice or trial performance of a play or other work for later public performance.</summary></entry></feed>