<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-01-22T17:15:01+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">etymology</title><subtitle>an open rehearsal space for unfinished thoughts</subtitle><author><name>ben</name><email>etymology@uchicago.edu</email></author><entry><title type="html">Rehearsal (n.)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/meta/rehearsal/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rehearsal (n.)" /><published>2018-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/meta/rehearsal</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/meta/rehearsal/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;(1570s) a practice or trial performance of a play or other work for later public performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The verb “to rehearse” (13c. “to repeat, give an account of”) comes from Old French “rehercier” (to go over again, repeat) which in turn derives from OFr. “herse” (harrow), a rake like implement which is dragged across plowed earth to break up clods, remove weeds, and cover seed. Similarly, rehearsal “goes over” a work, exposing and improving it. This sense of “to practice a work for later performance” comes from the late 16th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compare also “hirsute” (hairy, spiny) and “hearse” (a funeral coach), originally a wood or metal framework which held the mortuary cloth over the bier or coffin, called a “herse” for its resemblance to a the farm tool. The name became metonymic for the coffin, then the vehicle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somewhere between the practice room and the concert hall (between everyday speech and polished prose) lies a space where the constant tension between failure and inspiration upholds an extemporaneous performance without straining it. The performance could be a recital for friends, or a dialogue between peers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than speculate on the as yet unwritten content of this blog, I will simply hope that it be a space informal performances, a place to try out ideas before a forgiving (or silent) audience. Here, as in the old sense of “rehercier” I hope to comb through my thoughts, leaving behind tracks for new growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thank my friends for encouraging me, though they are not to blame for this (mis)adventure. Their advice has always been sound, and any error is my own. Particular thanks go to Emily for arguing that my blog could achieve something more than indecent academic exposure, and to Ronen for inspiring me to start. I am motivated by the thought that you might be reading this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-ben&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etymonline.com/word/rehearse&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>ben</name><email>etymology@uchicago.edu</email></author><category term="meta" /><category term="etymologies" /><category term="personal" /><summary type="html">(1570s) a practice or trial performance of a play or other work for later public performance.</summary></entry></feed>